NICOLAS ARAGON BARRERO

Email: nico.aragonbarrero@gmail.com

Nationality: Spanish

Date of birth: 03/01/1989

Github: @nicoarbar

Stack Overflow contributions: https://stackoverflow.com/users/9315630/nico-arbar

Location: Madrid, Spain - Available for relocation **Languages:** Bilingual in Spanish and English

SUMMARY

I am a **Cloud Data Architect** and **Lead Data Engineer** with experience in consulting in the endto-end process of developing and managing analytic applications along team of developers, product owners and stakeholders.

From analyzing the business requirements with the clients, to implementing and developing solutions by designing the architecture, the data model, developing ETL processes, doing code reviews and helping with the visualization of the data in the dashboards, and managing the developer team and mentoring junior developers. Always analyzing the quality and integrity of the data and the code in every step of the process and working with Agile and DevOps methodology. **SQL, Python, Pyspark, Git, VSCode** have been my day-to-day tools in my career.

In my free time I like learning more about cloud services, analytic and machine learning frameworks, leadership, and management, plus continuing to earn technical certifications.

TECHNICAL CERTIFICATIONS

- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate
- AWS Certified Developer Associate
- AWS Certified Data Analytics Specialty
- AWS Certified Machine Learning Specialty
- Azure Fundamentals
- Azure AI Fundamentals
- Azure Data Engineer Associate
- Azure Data Scientist Associate
- Google Cloud Digital Leader
- Databricks Data Engineer Associate

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: SQL, Python, Pyspark, bash scripting.

<u>AWS services:</u> S3, Athena, Redshift, Dynamo, Glue, Lambda, Step Functions, SNS, Secrets Manager, Cloud Watch, Cloud Trail, Sagemaker, Cloud Formation, Code Build, Code Commit, Code Deploy, Code Pipeline, SAM

Azure Services: Blob Storage, ADLS, Synapse, Databricks, Data Factory, Key Vault, Azure

Machine Learning, Azure Devops

Methodologies: CI/CD, Git, Agile Methodology

BI Tools: Teradata, SAP Data Services, Microstrategy, PowerBI

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Role: Data Architect and Lead Data Engineer

<u>Company</u>: Cognizant <u>Location</u>: Madrid, Spain

Period: February 2022 - Present

Responsibilities:

- Responsible for the Data Engineering backend and the developer team in a project of a big retailer company.
- Proposing architectural decisions in the backend.
- Analyzing the data based on the business requirements and designing the data model.
- Being in touch with the client every day to understand what they want to achieve and translating those requirements into code.
- Managing a small team of developers and establishing the standards for coding and testing in the repository. Pair programming with junior developers and mentoring them.
- Reviewing architectural decisions with the platform architect and proposing solutions
- Designing and coding ETL processes, doing code reviews, unit testing and optimizing code.
- Working with the Azure analytic services such as Databricks with Pyspark for data processing, ADLS as storage in delta tables, Azure Data Factory for orchestration, Synapse as a datawarehouse, and Azure Devops for the CI/CD pipelines.

Role: Data Engineer

<u>Company</u>: Indra (Minsait) <u>Location</u>: Madrid, Spain

Period: March 2018 - February 2022

Responsibilities:

- Analyzing the business requirements of the client to implement a datawarehouse and a datamart to analyze operational data.
- Designing and creating the data model, using an on-premise Teradata database, S3, Athena, Redshift and Dynamo on AWS.
- Designing the ETL process that goes from having the data in flat files from the S3 datalake to the datamart with a structured layer datalake. Using SAP Data Services, AWS Glue with Pyspark, Lambda functions and Step Functions.
- Helping with the data visualization and creating reports using Microstrategy Developer as a Business Intelligence tool.
- Attending and solving the possible issues in the data quality and integrity in the data flow from end to end, optimizing and code reviewing improving the performance of AWS Glue Jobs and SQL queries, that make up the ETL process and the reports in the visualization.
- Presenting the client different reports using data visualization and offering possible solutions based on their needs.

Role: Assistant to Ambassador

Company: Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Spain

Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: October 2015 - February 2016

Responsibilities:

- Assistant to the Spanish Ambassador for the Pacific Alliance office, Rafael Dezcallar de Mazarredo.
- Political analysis of the role of Spain in Latin America and the Pacific Alliance, and implementation of its policies and commercial activities.
- Organizing staff related issues such as meetings, preparing talking points in the agenda and developing proposals.

Role: Research Intern

Company: Vlaams Instituut voor Biotechnologie (VIB)

Location: Ghent, Belgium

Period: February 2013 - September 2013

Responsibilities:

- Research for my Master Thesis of Biochemistry: *Study of A20 in intestinal inflammation.*
- Researching the molecular pathways concerning NF-KB as a regulatory factor regarding inflammation, concerning the A20 protein and its regulation in inflammation response in the intestinal tract.
- Statistical analysis and experimental design.

EDUCATION

Degree: Master in Big Data and Business Analytics

University: IMF Business School / Universidad Camilo José Cela

Location: Online

Period: November 2018 – November 2020

Degree: Bachelor in Philosophy

University: Universidad Autonoma de Madrid

Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: September 2010 - July 2016

Degree: Bachelor in Biochemistry

University: Universidad Autonoma de Madrid

Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: September 2008 - July 2014

UNIVERSITY SCHOLARSHIPS TO STUDY ABROAD

Scholarship: Convenios Internacionales Scholarship

University: University of Melbourne **Location:** Melbourne, Australia **Period:** February 2015 – June 2015

Scholarship: CEAL Scholarship of Banco Santander

University: Instituto Tecnológico de Estudios Superiores de Monterrey

Location: Mexico City, Mexico

Period: August 2014 – December 2014

Scholarship: Erasmus Scholarship University: Ghent University Location: Ghent, Belgium

Period: September 2012 – September 2013